<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter vnto them of the Romish Church, by Peter du Moulin, minister in the reformed Church at Paris. Together with a true iubile or generall pardon of indulgence by the same author</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853922</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853922</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19325</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19325)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1064:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter vnto them of the Romish Church, by Peter du Moulin, minister in the reformed Church at Paris. Together with a true iubile or generall pardon of indulgence by the same author</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
                  <author>Goring, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for Mathew Lownes, dwelling in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Ry. Goring.</note>
                  <note>"The great iubile and pardon of full remission for all true Christians" has caption on D7v.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
LETTER
VNTO THEM
<hi>of</hi>
The Romiſh Church,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> PETER <hi>du</hi> MOVLIN, Miniſter
in the reformed Church at
<hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a true Iubile or generall
<hi>Pardon of Indulgence by the</hi>
ſame Author.</p>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Mathew Lownes,</hi>
dwelling in Paules Church-yard.
1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19325:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19325:2"/>
            <head>TO
The right worſhipfull,
Maſter VVILLIAM
HAKEVVILL, Eſquier, R. G. Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth
(as in dutie he is bound) all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
of grace and true
happineſs.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His little but excellent tract
of <hi>Monſieur du Moulins</hi>
being giuen mee to tranſlate
by your worthie brother
(who formerlie, as your Worſhip may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
did once ſet me aworke in the like
kinde vvith no ill ſucceſſe) and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous
<pb facs="tcp:19325:3"/>
to haue it patronized by ſome
good friend as the custome is, I ſoone
bethought mee how it might verie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptablie
paſſe vnder your name, if
ſo it would pleaſe you to grace my poore
endeuour, which in all humblenes I glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
offer vp vnto you: firſt, as a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
remembrance of your manie charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
fauours towardes mee; and then as
an earneſt of my willingnes to bee doing
as I am able.</p>
            <p>The diſcourſe of it ſelfe in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
is of worth enough to giue all good
men content, which loue Gods true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
together with the propogation and
increaſe thereof, and (as I hope) hath
receiued no greate ſoile or blemiſh by
paſsing through my handes.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes it was intended by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
man the Authour, eſpeciallie for
his owne countriemen of the Romiſh
Church: but alas who are ſo deafe as
they that will not heare, or blind like
them that will not ſee? Yet as hee ſaith
in the end of his diſcourſe, that <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam
ſuam liberauit</hi> in caſe it worke
<pb facs="tcp:19325:3"/>
not amongſt them his wiſhed effect; So
likewiſe if it paſſe into Engliſh vnder your
<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>au<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ur, <hi>vous aurez auſſi Monſieur ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ncè une
bonne oeuure.</hi> So trusting to
our Worſhips gentle acceptance, I ceaſe
further to trouble you in your moſt
worthie employments for the
common good; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
and euer much bounden,<lb/>
                  <hi>Ry. Goring.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19325:4"/>
            <head>A Letter to them of the
Romiſh Church, by Peter
du Moulin, Miniſter of GOD's
Word in the Reformed
Church of Paris.</head>
            <head type="sub">Tranſlated into Engliſh out of the French
Originall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Masters:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE things that I have to
repreſent to you, would
perhappes bee more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
from any other
hand than from mine: and yet I may
bee bould to ſay, that never did any
man ſpeak to you more void of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,
or more deſirous of your good
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19325:5"/>
and ſalvation. The Word of God,
from whence wee draw our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
commands us to love thoſe that
hate us, and to beleeve that thoſe
which doo perſecute us doo thinke
they doo God good ſervice. Every
ſpirit, which ſeeketh after the truth,
ought thus to be diſpoſed. Without
this, it is impoſſible to gather anie
fruit by our communication: for,
never doth any wound cloze up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
during the inflammation. And
even as in a houſe which is on fire,
thoſe which ſpeake are not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood:
ſo ſhall we never underſtand
one another, whil'ſt our ſpirits doo
burne with hatred and ſpleen. The
ſtudy of the ſacred Word of GOD
requireth a quiet ſpirit, which wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
waigheth things without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
againſt any mans perſon: for,
what reaſon is it to hate any bodie
becauſe hee goeth aſtray, or becauſe
wee think wee ſee more cleere than
hee?</p>
            <p>Now then, even as blinde-men
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19325:5"/>
are commonly wranglers and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick;
ſo alſo ſuch as are moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
receive leaſt inſtruction: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
hee that ſhall remedy this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
ſhall likewiſe appeaſe this fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſſe.
But, the evill is without
remedy in him that endeavoureth
to be ignorant, and feareth to know
the will of God, leſt hee ſhould bee
ſo much the more obliged to follow
it. This is (my Maſters) the diſeaſe
of this Age: in which, people make
profeſſion of following without
knowing, and to beleeve his Church
without knowing what the Church
ought to beleeve; and reſteth upon
the faith of other, being ignorant of
the rule of faith, which is the Word
of God: as if thoſe that lead us ought
to bee our warrants againſt GOD's
judgement, or as if it were a vertue
to beleeve in God by Attorney.</p>
            <p>Indeed, people ought to obey
their Guides, in caſe God bee their
Guide; and beleeve that which they
teach, if ſo bee that which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19325:6"/>
bee drawne from the Word of
God.<note place="margin">The Index of bookes forbidden, together with the rules which were made by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen thereto by the Tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Synod. The fourth rule. In as much as it is plainly ſeen by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that if the Bible bee every where ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bee read in the vulgar tongue without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſtraint, more hurt then good will thence ariſe, by occaſion of mens raſhnes. Hee that without ſuch like licence ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to read or have the Bible, may not have an abſolution of his ſinnes, vnleſſe hee firſt deliver it up into the hands of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</note> The which if they hide from
the people, and hinder the reading
thereof, it is a ſigne that they find
themſelves guilty; or that, in ſtead of
ſubjecting themſelves to this rule,
they will have the ſoveraign rule to
bee their authority. For, wherefore
ſhould the Word of God, contained
in holy Scriptures, bee a ſuſpicious
thing unto us, and as it were a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
book? Wherefore ſhould not
children bee permitted to ſee their
fathers Teſtament? The Apoſtle
Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath written his Epiſtles
to the people of Rome, of Corinth
and Epheſus, to the end they might
read them: wherefore then ſhould
Chriſtian people at this day bee de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prived
of the reading of them? The
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19325:6"/>
Catholike Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Where it is to be noted, that there it is ſpoken of Bibles tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated by Catholick Roman Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.</note> S.
<hi>Peter,</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> are written to
all the faithfull in generall: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
then ſhould not Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
read thoſe Letters which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
directed unto them, and are
written for their inſtruction? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
may they not read the writings
of the Prophets, as well as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of Berea? which, coming from
Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Sermon, went and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
it with the Scriptures. To
what end are Texts alleaged in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
if it bee not lawfull for the
Auditor to goe home and ſee in the
Scriptures,<note place="margin">Acts 17. 11</note> whether they bee truely
alleaged or no? A horrible thing,
that in thoſe Countries where the
Inquiſition raigneth, it is a crime
worthy the fire to have a Bible in
the vulgar tongue; whil'ſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the reading of fables is tolerated,
but whoredome alſo eſtabliſhed
there by law and politick regiment.
If ſo bee the Tranſlation bee not
thought true by the Pope, his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19325:7"/>
ſhould give order for a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation
fitting his judgement.</p>
            <p>To ſay, that ſome abuſe this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
is to accuſe the Apoſtles of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to have written their<note n="*" place="margin">The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did write in a language moſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</note> Epiſtles
to chriſtian people, without foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
that they might abuſe the ſame:
by the ſame reaſon, they might for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
the preaching thereof, becauſe
many doo abuſe it. Men abuſe even
the very goodnes of GOD. Nay,
which is more, it was never ſeene,
that any of the people did ever forge
any Hereſie through reading of the
Scripture. All our Hereſiarchs have
been perſons that have had place in
the Church. Now, if to reade the
holy Scripture, wee muſt have ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
leave given us, is it not a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
thing that wee may not obey
God but upon ſufferance, and that
God can have no ſervants without
the Biſhop of Romes permiſſion? Or
if they ſay, it is not for ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
to read them: I anſwer, that all
men are ignorant in religion before
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19325:7"/>
they read them, and that men may
not without impiety aſcribe any skil
unto themſelves in religion, beſides
or without the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Shake off then (my Maſters) this
ſcrupulous feare, by which God is
wronged, as if his Word were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious,
and a ſnare laid for weake
conſciences; leſt upon you bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed
the Prophecy of <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 5. 13</note>
               <hi>My people are in captivity, becauſe they bee
without knowledge:</hi> and the ſaying of
our Saviour, <hi>You erre, not knowing the
Scriptures.</hi> Let not this pretious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
bee wrung out of your hands;
this contract of our ſpirituall marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
with the Sonne of God: hould
them as ſuſpected perſons, who du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
this night of ignorance do hide
this heavenly Light, and in the mean
time light up their owne candles at
high-noon. Hope not to bee ſaved
by the faith of others: for, God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares
unto us,<note place="margin">Hab. 4. 2</note> that <hi>The iuſt ſhall live
by his owne faith:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 14</note> and that <hi>If the blinde
lead the blinde, they ſhall both fall into the
ditch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19325:8"/>
Now, that you may knowe that
they take the Scriptures away from
you, not to keep you in ſobriety, but
to detaine you in ignorance; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
that in the Roman Church they
read publikely unto you ſome chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of the Bible in a tongue which
you underſtand not. If in theſe chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
GOD were ſpoken unto, one
might excuſe it; ſaying, that GOD
underſtands all languages: but theſe
chapters are divine Lectures, in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
God ſpeaketh unto men. Tell me in
conſcience, wherefore ſhould God
bee a Barbarian unto us, and ſpeak to
us in an unknowne tongue? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
ſpeaks hee unto men, but to the
end they ſhould underſtand him?
Wherefore ſhould thoſe things, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
every where elſe would be eſteemed
ridiculous and againſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe,
bee thought good and comely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?
But, is it not a ſleight of the
enimy of our ſalvation; that he might
make Chriſtianity ridiculous, and
hinder the Word of God from bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19325:8"/>
underſtood of you? to the end
likewiſe that the threatning may be
accompliſhed which God uſeth to
a people with whom hee is angry,
<hi>I will ſpeak to this people by men of other
language,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 21.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; in a ſtrange tongue, and ſo
they ſhall not underſtand mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This evil hath produced another:
for, in taking away from you the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Scriptures which make men lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
they have given you Images,
which they call the books of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
men, becauſe they nouriſh igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance:
therewithall they buſie the
people, in ſtead of inſtructing them;
in ſtead of teaching them, they make
them paſſe-time. But becauſe that
againſt this ſame, the ſecond of Gods
commandements is expreſſe, which
forbids in matter of Gods ſervice to
make any Image, and to fall downe
before any repreſentation of anie
thing in Heaven or earth; and that
his Law, pronounced with thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
affrighteth even to this day this
ſuperſtition: theſe Doctours have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19325:9"/>
impoſed ſilence unto this Lawe of
God, and dare to raze out this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
out of thoſe books, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
and ſervice-bookes, which they
appoint them to uſe: A thing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
wee may ſuſpect our owne eyes,
and hardly beleeve when wee ſee it,
that very wormes of the earth have
made ſo bould as to correct the Law
of God pronounced with his owne
mouth; yea, that ſame Lawe, by
which they ſhall bee judged at the
laſt day.</p>
            <p>Vnto ſuch enterpriſes the holie &amp;
ſacred name of Church ſerveth as a
cloak. It is ſaid that the Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
erre; that ſhe is ſoveraign Iudge
of the points and doubts of faith;
that ſhee is the faithfull interpreter
of the Scripture. By which Church,
is underſtood not the Greek, nor the
Syrian, nor the African (although
more ancient &amp; more pure than the
Romane); but onely the Romane
Church, which, having never been
but a particular Church, cals herſelf
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19325:9"/>
the Vniverſall. By this meanes the
Church of Rome is becomne Iudge
in her own cauſe. The Greek Chur.
more ancient than the Roman, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth
that the Roman Church is
revolted and ſeparated from her,
producing againſt her her chaires,
her ſucceſſion, her antiquity. In this
conteſtation, the Romane Church
vanteth herſelf to bee Iudge, and ſo
will bee both Iudge and Party. In
the queſtion whether the Romane
Church can erre, ſhee herſelfe will
be Iudge; and (which is more) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
there is queſtion of deciding what
the Churches duty is, the Romane
Church will bee ſoveraigne Iudge,
to the end ſhee may have no other
lawes but of her owne eſtabliſhing,
and what ſhee will carve out for her
owne ſelf. And, moreover, when the
ſenſe and interpretation of the Lawe
of God lieth at the ſtake, ſhee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
herſelf the infallible expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
and reputes her owne interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of equall authority with the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19325:10"/>
Law of God; yet is it certaine, that
by this Law ſhee ſhall bee judged at
the later day. Now, there is no raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
ſo extravagant, as to put ſinners
for infallible judges of the ſenſe of
the Lawe, by which their ſinnes are
to be judged. What obedience think
you is the Soveraign Maſter to look
for, if his ſervants may ſay unto him,
Thou haſt indeed commanded us
that ſame, but wee interpret it thus,
and doo judge that thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
ought thus to bee underſtood;
and thou knoweſt, that wee are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
judges in ſuch matters, and
that our interpretations are of equal
authority to thy commandements?
By this reckoning, it were better to
bee ſervant than Maſter. By which
of theſe two (thinke you) ſhall the
Prelates of the Church of Rome be
judged at the laſt day? whether by
the Law of God, or by their owne
interpretations? I referre this to the
judgement of any man that hath but
the remainder of common ſenſe left
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19325:10"/>
him, or any ſpark of free and unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocupate
conceipt, which of the two
ought rather to be ſupream Iudge in
religion: whether God, ruling and
teaching the Church by his Word;
or the church, that ought to receive
this Word, and obey him. Who ſhall
rather be Iudge, the ſcripture which
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands there ſhould be a Church,
and giveth it lawes; or the Church,
which onely giveth atteſtation that
that is the Scripture? ſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering,
that even this teſtimony
may be given by a corrupt Church,
and diſobedient to this Scripture.
Who ſhall bee rather Iudge, the
Scripture which is one, and judgeth
without paſſion; or the Church,
which is divided into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
which cannot bee aſſembled,
and whoſe Paſtors are ſubject to am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
and avarice, and fitter to bee
had in ſuſpicion when there is anie
queſtion of their profit or authority?</p>
            <p>Heere (my Maſters) it is eaſie to
ſhewe you, that they lead you in a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19325:11"/>
way by which it is altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
you ſhould bee ſaved: for,
you are taught ſimply to beleeve the
Church of Rome, and without far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
enquiry to depend entirely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
her authority; and yet you are
deprived of all means to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
this Church, whereunto you
give credit, bee pure, and teacheth
true doctrine. For, how ſhould you
knowe that? ſhould it be by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Scriptures? yea, but this book is
not permitted you. At Rome and in
Spaine, to read in it, is no leſſe than
burning at a ſtake: or would you
knowe it by the Antients? thoſe are
greek &amp; latin books which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
underſtand not. What knowes
an artificer, or a woman, or an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman
amongſt you, whether the
Church teacheth conformably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Scripture? or if their church
bee ſuch as it was ſome 12. or 1500.
years ſince? or whether of a long liſt
of Popes pictured, the firſt have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved
as the laſt, and that the times
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19325:11"/>
have altered nothing? In briefe, you
have no other proof of the purity of
your church, but the witnes of your
Church it ſelf: whoſe Prelates, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
themſelves that they cannot
erre, in the meane time deprive you
of all means to diſcern of error from
truth; by hiding from you the rule
of truth, which is the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
But wherfore ſhould the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
Church rather have this perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
that the Greek or the Syrian
(more antient and more pure than
the Roman) founded by Ieſ. Chriſt
himſelfe, and by his Apoſtles; and
who alſo brag to have Saint <hi>Peters</hi>
chair? Doth the Scripture give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Roman Church any preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
above others? or doth it give
her the priviledge of not erring?</p>
            <p>From hence doe enſue two things
as cleere as the day: the one, that
your faith is grounded onely upon
the authority of men, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
that your religion is a humane
religion and not divine. Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19325:12"/>
ſaith, I beleeve the Goſpell and
the Word of GOD, becauſe the
Church ordaineth it, maketh the
Church more credible than God.
To doubt of Gods truth, is a leſſe
crime, than to make it depend upon
men. The other is, that, of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
witneſſes, you ground your
ſelves upon the worſt and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain:
for, you ſay, your Church
is good becauſe ſhee ſaith it, and ſo
doo make her Iudge in her owne
cauſe; not conſidering, that by this
word Church, you underſtand not
Chriſtian people, nor the generality
of Paſtors, but the Pope and ſome
fewe Prelates whoſe rules are called
Church-rules, although they tend
onely to the profit of the Clergie,
and the advancement of the Empire
of the Biſhop of Rome.</p>
            <p>And you poor ſoules, whom God
hath framed after his owne Image,
whom hee hath redeemed with the
blood of his Son, whom God ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth
by his Word, will you lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19325:12"/>
alwaies in this captivity? will
you heap up unto your ſelves the
wrath and indignation of the Lord,
by rejecting the ſalvation which is
propoſed you?</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, that the Roman Chur.
in certain points alleageth ſcripture,
and that between her and us there is
ſtrife about the interpretation: but
we make uſe of the Scripture in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
manner than thoſe which teach
you.</p>
            <p>For firſt, they are afraid the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
ſhould read the Scriptures: but
we exhort men thereunto.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they perſwade you, that
the Scripture is obſcure and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous:
but we ſay, all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
unto ſalvation are therein layd
downe with much clearneſs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they ſay that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
is an unperfect rule, they will
needs have another unwritten word,
and traditions of the Church equall
in authority to the Scripture: wee
(on the contrary) ſay, that the holie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19325:13"/>
Scripture can make us wiſe unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 15. 1</note>
and that wee ought not to bee
wiſe beyond what is written;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 4</note> and
that in that which is cleare in the
Scriptures, and needeth no interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained all the doctrines
neceſſary unto ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when wee alleage the
Scripture, we alleage it as ſoveraign
Iudge, and as it that ruleth the Chur.
and giveth her her authority: but
the Romane Church alleageth the
Scripture as a doctrine authorized
by the Church, and that you ought
to receive it becauſe the Church
hath ordained it.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, when wee interpret the
Scriptures, wee give not out our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations
for lawes as doth the
Roman Church, nor call our ſelves
judges or infallible interpreters of
the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Finally, when wee interpret the
Scriptures, wee draw our interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
from the Scripture it ſelf: but
the Roman Church draw their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19325:13"/>
from the unwritten
word and from tradition. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample:
wee expound thoſe words,
<hi>This is my body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He took the bread, gave it, &amp;c. Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me.</note> 
               <hi>By the bread which I give
you is the commemoration of my body;</hi> the
which expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is found in the text
it ſelf of the inſtitution of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
or by theſe words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,
1. <hi>Cor. 10. 16, The bread which
wee break is the communion of the body of
Chriſt.</hi> Your Teachers do not thus
interpret the Scriptures: for, they
draw their interpretations from the
unwritten word and from tradition.
When the Lord ſaid to <hi>Peter, I have
prayed that thy faith fail not;</hi> they ſay,
that by theſe words Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and
the Popes of Rome, his ſucceſſours,
were promiſed the vertue that they
could not erre: but the Scripture
ſpeaketh not of Popes or of Biſhops
of Rome, nor grants unto Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
any ſucceſſor in his Apoſtleſhip.
So <hi>Malachie</hi> ſpeaketh of a pure ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
which was to bee made in all
places;<note place="margin">Mal. 1. 11</note> This oblation, according to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19325:14"/>
the interpretation of theſe Maſters, is
the Maſſe; in which they ſay the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
of Chriſt is really ſacrificed. But
this interpretation is taken out of the
unwritten word: for, the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
ſpeaketh not of any Maſſe, nor
of the ſacrifice of the body of Ieſus
Chriſt, nor eſtabliſheth any ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers
in the Church to ſacrifice the
Son of God. So, when the Scripture
ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip one God, and
ſhalt ſerve him alone;</hi> The interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of theſe Maſters is, that God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth
onely the worſhip of <hi>Latria,</hi>
but not the adoratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Dulia,</hi> which
is an inferiour religious ſervice. But,
the Scripture ſpeaketh not of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration
of <hi>Dulia,</hi> nor of any other
religious ſervice then that which is
due unto God. Theſe are interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
which the Romane Church
draweth from the unwritten word,
which is at the diſcretion of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
Church, nor can bee learned
but from her mouth: for, I doo not
think there is any that ever hath ſeen
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19325:14"/>
all the inſtructions of this unwritten
word reduced into one body;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. in Barkl. c.</hi> 3. He thinkes not rightly of the chur. of the chur. of Chriſt, that admits nothing but what hee reads ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly to have bin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged or practiſed in the old chu. as if the Church of later time either ceaſt to be a chr. or hath not authority to expreſſe and declare, to decree alſo, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thoſe things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern faith &amp; Chriſtian manners.</note> and
that becauſe this word changeth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the age, and is fitted unto
the time, and that the Romiſh Chur.
hath power alſo to adde new articles
thereunto even in the points of faith.</p>
            <p>The greateſt miſchief is, that theſe
traditions and inſtructions of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written
word are not only additions
unto the Scripture, but alſo manifeſt
oppoſitions thereunto: whereof, the
Maſs alone doth furniſh us with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
examples. 1. For, Ieſus Chriſt,
adminiſtring the holy Sacrament of
the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> ſpake in a tongue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
of the ſtanders by: but the
Prieſt in his Maſſe ſpeaketh in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
language. 2. Ieſus Chriſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred
to all there preſent: but
the Prieſt oftentimes eateth &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
himſelfe alone. 3. Ieſus Chriſt
communicated the cup unto all, and
willed that all ſhould drink thereof:
but the Prieſt drinketh alone, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth
the chalice unto the people. 4.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19325:15"/>
Ieſus Chriſt offred nothing to God:
but the Prieſt prayeth in the Maſſe,
that God would be pleaſed with his
oblation. 5. Ieſus Chriſt made no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levation
of the hoſte: but the Prieſt
houldeth up an hoſte to bee adored.
6. In the inſtitution of this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
there is no ſpeech of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,
nor of ſacrificing the body of
Ieſus Chriſt: cleane contrary, the
Prieſt pretendeth the ſacrificing of
the body of Ieſus Chriſt in a reall &amp;
propitiatory ſacrifice for the living
and the dead alſo. 7. Vnder the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
of our Lord there were no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques
hid,<note place="margin">We beſeech thee, Lord, through the merits of the Saints, whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks wee have heer, and for the merits of all the Saints beſides, that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all our ſins.</note> nor the bones of any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch
or Prophet: on the contrary,
the Prieſt hath under the ſtones of
his Altar the bones of the dead, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
which reliques an Altar cannot
bee conſecrated: and ſo according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the Prieſt in his Maſſe craveth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
by the merits of thoſe Saints
whoſe bones lie hidden under that
Altar; a thing that Ieſus Chriſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
thought of. 8. Ieſus Chriſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19325:15"/>
that it was the fruit of the
Vine that hee drank: but the Prieſt
denies that it is ſo. 9. Ieſus Chriſt
will, that we make commemoration
of him: but the Prieſt pretendeth to
make Ieſus Chriſt himſelf. 10. Saint
<hi>Paul</hi> ſaith foure times, that we eat &amp;
break bread: on the contrary, the
Prieſt maintains, that we neither eat
nor break bread. 11. The Lord inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuteth
a Sacrament: but the Prieſt
celebrateth a Sacrifice. In a word,
the one adminiſtreth the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
the other ſingeth Maſſe, expreſly
made to diſ-figure the holy Supper
of our Lord.</p>
            <p>Theſe Maſters thinke themſelves
well fenſed with uſing a childiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination
in objecting unto us, that
ſeeing wee will imitate our Lord, we
ought all to celebrate the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
after ſupper, &amp; in a high cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
and not to admit of women: but
neither the place, nor the houre, nor
the ſex of the aſſiſtants, is either part
or eſſence of the action; and without
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19325:16"/>
any of theſe the action remaineth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire,
nor hath Ieſus Chriſt touching
the ſame given any rule, or forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
any circumſtance. But the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
which wee object againſt them, is in
things eſſentiall, and which change
the nature of the action; ſeeing that
thereby is introduced an adoration
not commanded nor practiſed by
the Apoſtles; and a ſacrifice eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
which our Lord hath not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained;
and an authorized ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
about dead mens bones; and a
publike repaſt changed into a private
Maſs; and the people fruſtrate of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
their ordinary ſervice;
and inſtructed to take God, and to
eat their Creator, &amp; adore the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
and deprived of one halfe of
the Sacrament, to wit the cup, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
Chriſt hath ſaid,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Drink ye all of this:</hi>
as alſo the Apoſtle commandeth the
people of Corinth to take the cup as
well as the bread.<note place="margin">Let a man prove him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo eat of this bread, and drink of this cup.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon wee propoſe a means
of agreement, which cannot bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19325:16"/>
but by him that loves diſcord,
or is thirſty of Chriſtian blood, or
which will war againſt God: for, all
Chriſtians confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſt
hath done well, and that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
amiſſe in his inſtitution, and
that even when it might bee lawfull
to celebrate the holy Communion
in ſome other faſhion then hee did;
yet all agree, that it would not bee ill
done to follow his example, ſpeak as
hee ſpake, and doo as he did. Now,
this is that which wee demand: and
certaine it is, that the Pope might
make an end of all conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions ſprung
from this point, which trouble and
divide Chriſtendome, if hee would
reſtore the holy Communion unto
the form in which our Lord did ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate
it; laying aſide all diſputes, &amp;
binding the people unto the example
of the Son of God. What incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities
or inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veniences ſoever might
bee alleaged againſt the ſame, could
not bee put in balance againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
which wee owe to Ieſus
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19325:17"/>
Chriſt, &amp; againſt the peace of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome,
and the re-union of that
rupture and ſeparation of people,
which hath cauſed ſo many troubles,
and ſpilt ſo much blood, and which
goareth the ſide of the Ro. Church
as well as ours, expoſing it to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence
of Turks and Infidels.</p>
            <p>Every ſpirit that is not preoccupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
will eaſily acknowledge, that this
is the language of truth: wherewith,
leſt your conſciences ſhould bee tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
they uſe a device, namely, to
repreſent unto you our religion alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
other then it is, and paint it
out unto you like a hideous monſter,
and to make us ſpeake things wholly
againſt our beleef. And thereupon,
many amongſt you are of ſo eaſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leef,
as to chuſe rather to learne what
our religion is by our enemies invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,
than by our owne confeſſion;
yea, after wee have proteſted, not to
beleeve any thing of all they father
upon us, yet would they make us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
our ſelves, that wee beleeve
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19325:17"/>
that which wee beleeve not: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
they juſtifie us before they bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.
For, thereby they privily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
that our religion truely propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
cannot bee encountred; and that
if it were repreſented in as true co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,
at the very firſt it would make
a ſtrong impreſſion in the minde of
the Auditor through the evidence of
the truth thereof. They tell you, 1.
that our religion teacheth, that good
works are not neceſſary; 2. that the
Elect may without danger licence
themſelves to doo evill; 3. that God
gives no recompenſe to good works;
4. that God conſtraineth our willes,
and forceth them unto good; 5. that
we accuſe God of injuſtice, as having
given us a law which wee cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh;
6. that wee are enemies to
the Saints and the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> 7.
that for the underſtanding of the
Scriptures, every one of us vanteth
to have a particular inſpiration; 8. and
that wee deny the Almightineſſe of
God in the Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19325:18"/>
Is not this all falſe, and contrary to
our beleef? 1. Our religion teacheth,
that good works are neceſſary unto
ſalvation: for, men goe not to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
by the way of hell, nor unto the
Kingdome of God by ſerving the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell.
2. Our religion teacheth, that
the predeſtinated unto ſalvation
are alſo predeſtinate to live holily.
To ſay, <hi>I may abandon my ſelf unto evill
ſeeing I am elected,</hi> it is the language of
a reprobate, who will be bad becauſe
God is good, and who makes of the
grace of God, which is a ſpurre unto
vertue, a pillow to ſleep upon in all
vice. 3. Our religion beleeveth, that
God rewardes good works, but with
a ſalary freely given. 4. We beleeve
that God conſtraineth not our wills,
but bendeth them, and cauſeth them
to give themſelves willingly unto
good. 5. We eſteem it not a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
that God ſhould demand at mans
hands that which hee cannot, when
man doth owe it, and when his una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe
commeth of his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19325:18"/>
fault. 6. We honor the Saints as they
honoured the Saints that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
them. 7. For the underſtanding
of the Scriptures, wee content our
ſelves with that which we finde clear
in them, and leave particular inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
to frantick perſons. 8. Wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
not the omnipotency of God in
the Euchariſt, but rule our ſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to his will: wee uſe the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
of the Communion, not to
make Ieſus Chriſt, but to honor him;
not to make his body deſcend unto
us, but to elevate our hearts to him.
Wee undertake not to take GOD in
this life, but content our ſelves that
hee take us at our deaths. Wee feare
not, that God can fall to the ground,
or be ſtolne away, or gnawn by mice,
or eaten by his enemies. We beleeve
not that the Son of God and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell
could enter both together into
<hi>Iudas;</hi> nor that Ieſus Chriſt did eat
himſelf, ſeeing it was nothing neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
for our ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Our religion is a religion which
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19325:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19325:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19325:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19325:20"/>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19325:21"/>
acknowledgeth no other head of the
Church but Ieſus Chriſt, nor other
rule of faith then his Word, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
propitiatory ſacrifice then his
Death, nor other purgatory then his
Blood, nor other merit than his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
            <p>It is a religion, which would have
the people to read the word of God,
becauſe we fear not to finde our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation
therein; and which ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
in a knowne tongue, for that it
is not aſhamed of her beleef.</p>
            <p>It is a religion, which holdeth fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
to bee in abſtinence, and not in
diſtinction of meats: wee faſt for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
of humility, and not in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of merit or ſatisfaction: wee bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
not other mens ſatisfactions; but
wee beleeve with the Apoſtle, <hi>That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
one ſhall bear his owne burden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a religion, which diſtruſting
her owne works beleeveth in Gods
promiſes, which preacheth the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
and not the doubt of her ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
recommendeth an humble aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19325:21"/>
and not an arrogant perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
by which they that ſet forth their
merits, make a profeſſion to doubt of
their ſalvation.</p>
            <p>It is a religion, wherein men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
they have often don that which
God hath forbidden, farre from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
done more than hee hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded;
ſo farre from dooing over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much,
as that they faile even of that
which is neceſſary: they pretend not
to make God a debter by their works
of ſupererogation, but confeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
debters through their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>It is a religion, which, in ſtead of
forming of ſtones to the likeneſſe of
man, endeavoureth to reforme man
unto the image of God; which, in
ſtead of adoring a wooden croſſe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oreth
the crucified, truſteth in his
paſſion, and glorieth in his reproach.</p>
            <p>It is a religion, which beleeves not
that God taketh pleaſure to torment
the ſoules of his children in burning
fire, and to puniſh them for faults al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19325:22"/>
ready pardoned, and for which Ieſus
Chriſt hath fully ſatisfied by puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
which ſerveth not to amend
the ſinner, but to content the Iuſtice
of God.</p>
            <p>It is a religion, which maketh not
her praiers by count, nor placeth the
power of it in the number of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition
of one &amp; the ſelf ſame prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;
but in the faith and diſpoſition of
the heart.</p>
            <p>It is a religion, which holdeth that
faith conſiſteth not in ignorance, but
in knowledge: which equally diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth
holy things to rich and poor;
not like as in the Romane Church,
whoſe diſpenſations &amp; letters of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution
are ſold, and particular Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
never ſaid for him that hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
to give.</p>
            <p>Briefly, it is a religion which hath
leſſe ſplendour without, but more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidneſs
within; which will endure
narrow ſifting; which ordaineth few
ceremonies, but giveth much inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19325:22"/>
You wil heer ſay, But theſe things
are new. How new, ſeeing Ieſus
Chriſt and his Apoſtles have thus
taught? Indeed theſe are new to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
brought up in an inveterate er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour;
and you knowe, that healing is
alwaies newer than ſicknes: but wee
muſt alwaies goe up to the ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head
of truth; in compariſon of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>,
all ould errour is new. Never did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
man oppoſe himſelfe to any roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
errour ſettled by long cuſtome,
who hath not been accuſed of novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
And this reproach of novelty is
very unſeemly in their mouthes who
hide from the people the true Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
which is the holy Scriptures;
and who to this day maintaine, that
the Church can make new ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
touching faith; and, by the
Church, underſtand no other but the
Roman, who in the very firſt time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the Apoſtles cannot ſhewe one
man of their religion; &amp; who knowe
that in all Antiquity there is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
made of excluding the people
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19325:23"/>
from the cup, nor of forbidding from
the reading of the Scriptures, nor of
reading the Scriptures unto them in
an unknowne tongue which they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
not, nor of picturing the
Trinity, nor of adoring Images, nor
the Hoſte, with the adoration of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria,</hi>
nor of private Maſſes, nor of the
Biſhop of Romes Court, nor of his
Indulgences and Church-Treaſure,
nor of his power to depoſe Kings, &amp;
draw ſoules out of Purgatory, nor of
many other new corruptions which
they plaiſter over with the fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
title of Apoſtlique traditions,
as if they came from the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>The themſelves, who thus vaunt
of Antiquity, are thoſe which uſe the
antient Doctours moſt courſely, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring
and condemning them upon
ſlight occaſion: who will that the
Fathers ſhould be interpreters of the
Scriptures, in caſe they themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
may be the fathers interpreters,
and the Iudges of Antiquity; &amp; who
not only condemn every Father per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19325:23"/>
but alſo whole Councels
where the Fathers ſpeake in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            <p>Three univerſall Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>Honorius,</hi> Biſhop of Rome, for <note place="margin">Cotton in the preface of his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution ſpeaks thus of theſe two univerſall Councels.</note> an heretique: but, at this day they
maintain, that thoſe Councels miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves.<note place="margin">Greece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in the year 388. to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy Sea, &amp; to thwart the Biſhop of Rome, giving him the Biſhop of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople for a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</note> At the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
of Conſtantinople, in the yeare
381. there were a hundred and fiftie
Orthodox Biſhops, and 630. in the
Councell of Chalcedon, the yeare
450. Neither this great number, nor
their great Antiquity, hindreth our
adverſaries from condemning all
thoſe Fathers, for equalling the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe
of Conſtantinople to him of
Rome in eccleſiaſticall matters.</p>
            <p>And it is marvelous how theſe men
dare ſpeak of Councels,<note place="margin">Afterwards in the year 450. they ſaid they had the ſame privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</note> ſeeing they
knowe, the day &amp; night are not more
contrary than the ancient Councels
and the new, in which the Pope ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
and ordaineth all: but the other
biſhops give their opinion only, with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19325:24"/>
bowing of the head in ſigne of appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bation.
At the beginning of which,
they lay down the holy Scripture at
the Popes feet; in witnes, that the
Word of God is ſubject unto him:
where the Pope is ſeated on a high
Throne, having the Emperor ſitting
at his feet. In brief, wee may ſee by
the practice of theſe later Councels,
and above all by the Councel of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
and the laſt of Lateran, and by
the book of ſacred ceremonies, that
a Councell now within theſe few A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
is no other than a papal conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
though with more ſoleminity:
whereas in the antient Councels, the
biſhop of Rome durſt not be preſent,
and his deputies ordinarily had no
precedencie there nor authority; far
from ordaining, that no book ſhall be
canonicall without the Popes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
and that all Kings ſhould kiſs his
feet; and to declare, that there is no
other name under Heaven but that of
the great Biſhop:<note place="margin">Annal. Baron.</note> which are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees
of the Roman Councell under
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19325:24"/>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh,<note place="margin">Anno. 1078</note> the yeare 1076.
Briefly, it is certain, that they which
buzze in your eares the Fathers and
Councels, do it not becauſe the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients
are favourable unto them; but
becauſe they knowe that the people
can knowe nothing of them, and that
they muſt needs in thoſe things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
themſelves unto them. But, as
for the Scripture, which you ought
to knowe, and which ruleth all the
Fathers, it is that which is forbidden
you. In ſumme, yeares are no rules,
and lying is ever ſince the beginning
of the world. The Church is not in
a Countrey, of cuſtome; but, where
the written truth is. There is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription
againſt divine truth: yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
in the time of the Apoſtles the
myſtery of iniquity was a-brewing;
how far ought it now then to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced?
And indeed as wel the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
as the paſtors of the Ro. Church
have theſe many Ages cried out, that
their Church had need of reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
In the Councell of Pyſa, held in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19325:25"/>
the yeare 1411, Pope <hi>Alexnder</hi> the
fift, in the twentieth Seſſion, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
ſolemnly to intend the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Church, and to aſſemble
for that purpoſe the moſt learned of
all Nations. A while after, was held
a Councell at Senes, the yeare 1423.
where the propoſition of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
of the Church was revived,
and then put off to another time: for,
they ſaw they could not ſtir this ſtone
without ſhaking the papall ſeat.</p>
            <p>That which the great ones would
not doo, God hath performed by the
hands of little ones; uſing unhoped
for means to expoſe unto the view of
the world the doctrine of ſalvation
maugre al the machinations of Satan.</p>
            <p>Vnto thoſe that have endeavored,
and do yet endeavour to perfect this
work, you are thus much beholding,
as that the holy Scripture, which
the people ſaw not heertofore, is now
tranſlated into the vulgar tongue, and
that the Spirit of God ſpeakes it; ſo,
as none can be ignorant of the Word
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19325:25"/>
of God, but he that hood-winks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
leſt hee ſhould ſee the light. You
are alſo thus much more beholding
unto them, that the Pope doth leſſe
tyrannize over you than he did ſome
foure or five hundreth yeares ſince,
and that your ſervitude is by a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
leſſe burdenſome.<note place="margin">Such Buls are found in Math. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and in the 3. Tome of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, at the end of the Councell of Lateran vnder In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent the third.</note> For, in thoſe
daies the Pope gave to the French,
which armed themſelves for him and
at his commandement, beſides the
remiſſion of all their ſins, a degree of
glory in Paradiſe above others:
whereas now if he ſhould ſend them
to goe into a farre Countrey upon a
Croyſada, to fight againſt Hereticks,
or to take-in ſome Townes of their
neighbours to the Popes uſe, as was
done not very long ſince, you your
ſelves would mock at his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.
In former times, when any
King angred him, his cuſtome was to
interdite his Kingdome; and ſo put
(as far as in him lay) many millions
of perſons out of the communion of
the Church, cauſe all divine ſervice
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19325:26"/>
to ceaſe in a large Countrey, cauſe
the Bels to bee ſtill, hinder Burialls,
and to expoſe the Countrey in preie
to him could firſt conquer it. Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
was ſix years and a half in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,
in the time of King <hi>Iohn:</hi> but,
now-a-daies he drawes no more that
weapon; leſt, beſtirring himſelfe too
hard, hee overturne his owne chair,
which the doctrine of the goſpell
hath already much ſhaken.</p>
            <p>You owe them moreover this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation,
that you ſee not (as in the
time of <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth, and <hi>Leo</hi> the
tenth) Pardoners to run from houſe
to houſe through France, who for
half a crown ſould every one remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of all their ſins, and deliverance of
a ſoule out of Purgatory.</p>
            <p>The time hath bin, that in France
there was no ſpeech but of miracles,
and of Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire, and of the
apparition of damned ſoules, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
returning from Purgatory: of
which illuſions the greater part is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
at the Sunne-riſe of the holy
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19325:26"/>
Scriptures, which the night of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
had hidden. And if now they
doo any petty miracles, it is in ſecret,
and never in our ſight: for, before a
man that feareth God, and knoweth
him, Satan is as it were afflicted, and
loſeth his fenſe-play; yea, even your
owne Magiſtrates have puniſht theſe
deceivers.</p>
            <p>There bee but a few amongſt you
that doo wholly beleeve your owne
religion, but doo finde ſome fault in
the Romiſh Church: for indeed, it
would be a hard matter to endure the
decrees and gloſſes which ſay, that
<note n="a" place="margin">Tit. 8 de Praebend. cap. Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit. According to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our power we may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpenſe above law. Where the Gloſſe alſo; The Pope doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Apoſtle; as alſo againſt the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as alſo in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Gloſſa. diſt. 34. can. lector. The Pope can diſpenſe againſt the Apoſtle. Et cauſa 23. qu. 1. can. Sunt quidam, The Gloſſe hath it thus: Hee (the Pope) diſpenſeth in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, by interpreting it.</note> the pope is above law and right, and
that <hi>he can diſpenſe againſt the Apoſtle,
and against the goſpell;</hi> and which cals
<note n="b" place="margin">Gloſſa extrav. Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inter. Our Lord god the Pope.</note> the Pope, god; and<note n="c" place="margin">Concil. Lat. ultimum ſeſſ. 9. The countenance of thy divine Majeſty. Bellarm. in Barkl. c. 31. Chriſt gaue to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in a good ſenſe, power to make of ſinne no ſinne; and of no ſinne, ſinne.</note> the divine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19325:27"/>
or thoſe fabulous Legends,
which compare and equall in many
things, S. <hi>Dominick</hi> and S. <hi>Francis</hi> with
Ieſus Chriſt; or the opinion of thoſe
which muffle themſelves with the
habit of S. <hi>Francis</hi> when they are on
their death-beddes, ready to give up
the ghoſt, becauſe (ſay their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors)
that this garment is as good as
aſecond baptiſme: nor the gadding
of poor people 200. leagues off, after
pardons, ſeeing the remiſſion of ſins
is offered to us at home by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
of the goſpell: nor thoſe that
teach, that the Pope can make that
which is ſin to bee no ſinne, and that
which is no ſin to be ſin. And certain
it is, that though wee ſhould hould
our peace, yet the truth doth ſpeake
in the conſciences of many which
are held in this captivity for feare of
men, and for their domeſtick affairs:
for, the divell tickles men by the
panch, and rockes them a ſleep with
pleaſures and honours; from whence
it coms to paſſe, that the ſparks of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19325:27"/>
knowne truth are ſmother'd in them;
or, if they be not quenched in them,
they burn &amp; torture the conſcience,
and make them more culpable, not
onely for having buried their talent
of the knowledge of God, but even
for having diſſipated it; for having
bin aſhamed to confeſs the Sonne of
God before men, and not defending
his cauſe in time of need; for beeing
more afraid of mens diſpleaſure, than
to offend God, whoſe promiſes are
certain, his threatnings horrible, and
judgements eternall and inevitable:
who having now in our daies done ſo
many marvellous things, to build up
again the ruines of his Church, will
not ſurely leave unpuniſhed thoſe
which endeavour to trouble his work,
and who go purpoſely aſtray at high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon.</p>
            <p>All this diſcourſe (my Maiſters)
proceedeth from nought elſe but a
ſervent deſire that wee have of your
ſalvation, and that God might be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:
for, wee have heerein no other
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19325:28"/>
intereſt but your happineſſe; ſeeing
that for defending this cauſe we are
like to purchaſe nothing but trouble,
hatred and diſcommodity. Wee ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
deſire a great deale more to live
in peace and amity with our fellow-citizens
under one ſelf-ſame religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
if wee might doo it without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe
to God. Nor ceaſe wee to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
the Father of mercy, whoſe
compaſſions ſurmount our iniquties,
that hee would pardon thoſe which
hate us, that hee would touch their
hearts with repentance, and inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
their underſtandings with his
light, to knowe the day of their viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
and the way of eternall ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
leſt in the end he turn away his
favour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a people which turn their
backs upon him; and pour out a dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
more thick than the former upon
a nation enraged againſt the light of
the goſpell.</p>
            <p>If theſe conſiderations ſhall move
any one, it will bee a great joy unto
mee, and an ample reward for my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19325:28"/>
if it ſhall happen otherwiſe,
wee ſhall have at leaſt delivered our
owne ſoules, freed our conſciences,
and born witnes in this hart-harned
Age, until the Son of God com from
Heaven to heare our griefs, and
deliver his children, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
every one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to his worke.
To him be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
end.
Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19325:29"/>
            <head>THE
Great Iubile and Pardon
of full remiſsion for all
true Chriſtians.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He true pardon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
of all ſinnes is
made <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the aboundant
mercy of God, who par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth
vs all our ſinnes by one alone
Ieſus Chriſt in the ſhedding of his
bloud.<note place="margin">Luk. 1</note>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 14</note>
               <note place="margin">Ma. 1. 2. 6</note>
            </p>
            <p>For hee is the propitiation of all
the ſinnes of the world, and hath
manifeſted himſelfe by taking our
fleſh vpon him, alſo dying and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
our ſinnes in his bodie to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19325:29"/>
them,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1</note> (to the end hee might
purge vs from the ſinnes vnto the
which wee were bound) beleeuing
in him who is the Lamb without
ſpot once offered for all. In ſuch
ſort as no oblation of ſacrifice is
now anie more needfull heereafter
to abſolue vs from our ſinnes.<note place="margin">Parali. 3</note> The
which Lamb hath been made to vs
of God,<note place="margin">Iohn 1</note> wiſedom, Iuſtice, ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
and redemption, by which he
hath aboliſhed and whollie brought
to nought our folly,<note place="margin">Apoca. 1. 4</note> iniuſtice,<note place="margin">Ro. 4. 1.</note> abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
and obligation with w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God
the father hath giuen vs all things.
Vnto which pardon he himſelf doth
inuite vs aſwel by his Prophets as by
his Euangeliſts, ſaying; All yee that
be athirſt com vnto the great ſpring,<note place="margin">Tim. 1</note>
and who haue no monie make haſte
to com,<note place="margin">Iohn. 18 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> buy yee, drin yee, and eate
yee.</p>
            <p>Item, If anie bee adrie, Let him
come to mee and drink.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">Mat. 11. 28</note> Com vnto me all ye that are
wearie and heauis loden, and I will
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19325:30"/>
refreſh you.<note place="margin">Iohn 16. 23</note> And for our aſſurance
ſaith thus vnto vs: If your demande
anie thing of my father in my name
he will giue it you. And of whome
the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 7</note> Wherefore alſo he
can fully ſaue them which come
neere vnto him, alwayes lyuing to
make interceſſion for them.<note place="margin">Acts 4.</note> Saint
Peter ſaith there is no other name
giuen vnder heauen vnto men, by
which wee muſt bee ſaued,<note place="margin">Gala. 1</note> nor is
there ſaluation in any other:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
the Bull followeth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Theſe are the great Pardons and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences
of full remiſsion of ſinne and
puniſhment, giuen vnto all the Church
and Houſe of God, that is, to all faithfull
Chriſtians, vnder heauen.</head>
               <p>BY the authoritie and vertue of
the Commaundements of our
holie Father God the Creator our
ſoveraigne Lord,<note place="margin">Pſa. 109</note> &amp; by Ieſus Chriſt
our ſoueragine Paſtor &amp; euerlaſting
Biſhop,<note place="margin">Mar. 16</note> you are commaunded and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19325:30"/>
expreſly enionin'd by your holy obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
that you reade,<note place="margin">Luc. 9. 10</note> vnderſtand, &amp;
giue notice vnto euerie one, of the
great priuiledges, remiſſions, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons
of ſin &amp; puniſhment giune for
euer by God the father,<note place="margin">Pſal. 18</note> to al faithful
&amp; true ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt who
with al their hartes will render them
ſelues vnto him,<note place="margin">Act. 3. 4. 5. 6</note> faithfullie belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
and hoping for euerlaſting life
by his moſt precious bloud:<note place="margin">Luc. 11. &amp; 28</note> who
hath ſent his Apoſtles through all
the world to preach and declare his
holie goſpell and good tidings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning
the remiſſion of our ſinnes,
confirming their wordes by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
which the Lord wrought by
them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37</note> by the which wee haue full
Iubile &amp; generall pardon of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and ſinne;<note place="margin">Ier. 23</note> as his moſt holie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
had ordained euen before the
creation of the world and promiſed
by his Prophets;<note place="margin">Gal. 3</note> That at all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie
time and tymes, in all places &amp;
as often as we miſerable ſinners ſhall
acknowledge our pouertie and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19325:31"/>
beleeuing in him without
doubting,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 8</note> &amp; crauing pardon of him,
wee ſhall haue what wee deſire: and
all to ſhew his maruelous bountie
and mercie which hee intendeth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
vs for his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt
his ſake,<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 9. 7. 8 &amp; 12</note> how great ſinners ſoeuer we
bee; who beeing mooued with pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
conſidering the bottomleſs gulfe
of all euill in the which wee were
held by the diuell,<note place="margin">Pet. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and ſubjects and
ſlaues vnto him by our owne wills,
did ſend his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt at
that tyme which hee had appointed
when all wickedneſſe raigned,<note place="margin">Rom. 6</note> and
that all the world through ſin were
his mortall enimies;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3</note> and that to make
vs knowe what great charitie hee
bore to vs his enemies that we might
bee iuſtified and made cleane by his
bloud,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 1</note> and to preſerue vs from his
great furie.<note place="margin">Acts. 2.</note> By the which Ieſus
Chriſt our true Paſtor and Biſhop,
the father of mercy hath opened the
ineſtimable Treaſure of grace <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5</note> and
mercie <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1</note> which is the Treaſure of all
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19325:31"/>
faithfull Chriſtians vnder Heauen,
to the end that all thoſe which truſt
and firmely beleeue that this bloud
was ſpilt for the remiſſion of their
ſinnes, might be ſaued and deliuered
from the ſnares of the diuell.<note place="margin">Gal. 1</note> And ſo
hereafter in ſteed of ſinning wee
might doe good works like vnto our
Redemers, in louing our neighbours
yea euen our enemies, euen as Ieſus
Chriſt hath loued vs,<note place="margin">Iam. 2</note> which were
his enemies,<note place="margin">Deut. 1</note> &amp; therefore gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
vnto death for vs;<note place="margin">Leuit. 9</note> and that we
ſhould bee helpfull vnto all in all we
can,<note place="margin">Mat. 22</note> with as free and good a will as
hee hath done good vnto vs, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
reſpect vnto the rewarde, but
onelie vnto Ieſus Chriſt. And to the
end ye ſhould not thinke that theſe
Pardons and Indulgences bee falſe
&amp; counterfeit, we will hereafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
recite the witneſſes which
were preſent when they were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
beeing all credible perſons, and
who were all expreſſly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to beare witneſſe therof vnto all
in generall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19325:32"/>
               <head>The Witneſſes of the Premiſſes.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, as concerning the ould Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament:
Moyſes witneſſeth in
his booke of Geneſis, and other
following, in divers places, That by
Ieſus Chriſt (of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,
Iſack, Iacob, Iuda,</hi> and <hi>Dauid)</hi> all people
ſhall receiue bleſſing and ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Item,<note place="margin">Eſay. 19. 2 33. 35. 43. 18. &amp; 53</note> 
                  <hi>Eſaie, Ieremie, Ioel, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chay,
Malacky,</hi> doe witneſſe, That
the ſaluation of Iſraell and of the
elect people of God is in Ieſus
Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ioel. 2</note> Secondly,<note place="margin">Mich. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that in the new
Teſtament,<note place="margin">Mala. 2</note> Saint Mathew witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
that our great Biſhop Ieſus
Chriſt ſaith, I am not come to bee
ſerued, but to ſerue, and to giue my
life for the redemption of manie.
Item,<note place="margin">Mat. 9. 20. &amp; 26</note> Behould my bloud which
ſhall bee for the remiſſion of ſinnes.
Item, hee ſaid vnto one ſicke of the
Palſey that he ſhould beleeue in him,<note place="margin">Mar. 9. &amp; 16</note>
and his ſinnes were forgiuen him.
The like vnto the ſick woman, vnto
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19325:32"/>
the Leper, vnto the Blind and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
Saint Marke witneſſeth alſo,
that Ieſus ſaid vnto the father of the
Poſſeſſed, If thou canſt beleeue, all
things are poſſible vnto him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth.
Item, in another place,
Whoſoeuer will beleeue and bee
baptiſed ſhall bee ſaued. And
in manie other places, Saint Luke
witneſſeth, ſaying: Bleſſed bee the
Lord God of Iſraell: for hee hath
viſited &amp; redeemed his people.<note place="margin">Luc. 12. 24</note> Item
Behold I bring you tidings of great
ioy vnto all people, to wit, that this
daie is borne the Sauiour which is
Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ioh. 13. 5</note> Item, it is written, So it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houed
that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer
death and riſe againe, and ſo enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
his glorie, and that men ſhould
preach euerie where in his name re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
and forgiuneſs of ſinnes.
Saint Iohn witneſſeth that Saint
Iohn Baptiſt did publicklie approue
Ieſus Chriſt, ſaying: Behould the
Lamb of God which taketh awaie
the finnes of the world. Item who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19325:33"/>
belueeth in Ieſus Chriſt the
ſon of God, he hath euerlaſting life.
Item, Verclie I ſaie vnto you, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
heareth my word and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
in him that ſent mee, hee hath
euerlaſting life, and commeth not in
to iudgment,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2</note> but paſſeth for<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death
vnto life.<note place="margin">Apoc. 1</note> Item, Wee haue an aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
vnto God the father euen Ieſus
Chriſt: and he is the propitation for
our ſinnes, who hath loued and
waſhed vs from our ſins in his bloud.
And in manie places of the goſpel, &amp;
in the Epiſtles of Saint Paul he wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth
in manie texts: &amp; namely to
the Hebrewes,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.</note> where hee ſaith, Ieſus
purgeth awaie ſinne;<note place="margin">Actas <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Saint Peter alſo
ſaying: It is Ieſus Chriſt by whome
wee haue remiſſion of our ſinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concluſion of theſe Pardons.</head>
               <p>OVr holie father God the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,
who euer hath been and
ſhall bee: hath confirmed all the
graces,<note place="margin">Iudith 1</note> pardons and priuiledges of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19325:33"/>
thoſe reuerend Legats aboue menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned:
and excommunicateth all hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers,
murmurers and gainſayers of
thoſe ſaid pardons and indulgences.<note place="margin">Deut. 18.</note>
Hee which ſhall not heare my great
Prophet,<note place="margin">Gal. 1</note> ſhall bee raced out of the
booke of life. And Saint Paul: If we
or an Angell from Heauen preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
other thing then that which wee
haue declared and preached, let him
be accurſed. And therfore we reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
vnto you this noble and moſt
certaine pardon:<note place="margin">Iam. 2.</note> for it is that true
pardon which maie be got without
gold or ſiluer by a liuelie faith which
kindleth a charitie in all thoſe which
attaine vnto it, and ſtirreth them vp
to giue almes vnto all in want, and
render to each one that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth
vnto them:<note place="margin">Phil. 4</note> vnto this alſo
tendeth the lawe and the Prophets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Giuen</hi> in the ſupreame &amp; ſoueraine
Court of Paradiſe, euer ſince the
firſt beginning of the world.</p>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19325:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:19325:34"/>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
